Robert H. Taylor Collection of English and American Literature, 1280s-1958 (bulk 1800s-1930s ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- Series 4: Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts, 1280-1599; 22 manuscripts
  - Prayer Book, circa 1584; 23; AM 2016-50; 1 volume 259 pages 16.0 x 10.9 cm; 8vo Text written in Cursiva humanistica (Italic) and a calligraphic English Secretary bookhand, mostly in black ink with red, green, and brown inks used throughout, and margins ruled in red. The paper has a watermark sim
    1r-12v: Calendar, Use of Sarum. Marginal notes on English rulers from William the Conqueror (r. 1066-1087) to Queen Elizabeth I (r. 1558-1603). Each month concludes with a quatrain of medical advice in red or green ink. For example, December has the following verses: "To end with December of force wee must / Whole counsell is warme meates to use. / Too flye much wyne and banish lust / And never the gifts of God to abuse." For January 23, there is a note "terme begins" in red ink, referring to the Hilary term in the English legal court calendar. On fol. 13r, at the end of the calendar, is a table listing dates for Easter, Shrove Tuesday, and Leap Year, 1584-1607.
    14r-129r: Prayers in English. Some mention particular people or uphold Queen Elizabeth and the Church of England against all foe: (fol. 100v) "A praier to the Father, to the Sonne, and to the holy Ghjost, compiled & made by the Skelton," referring to the poet John Skelton (ca. 1463-1529); (fols. 113r-v) "A praier against the aduersaries of the Church"; (fol. 113v-114r) "A praier against the dissensions which do arise in the Churche"; (fol. 114r) "A prayer for the preservation of the Queen from Traiterus practises compiled by Mr Thomas Barwick," an English Catholic who in 1581 at Gonville and Caius College, Cambridge, opposed "dissimulation" by Catholic Recusants and declared himself openly to be a "Papist. There are notes on religious subjects (fols. 103v-110v), such as "The tenne Commaundementes with a brefe and shorte exposition of them." Several prayers are for Queen Elizabeth: (fol. 39r-v) "Queen Elizabeth encrease in her my all heart, true faith, godlie zeal, loue of the same, And graunt her victory ouer all her enemies; a longe, prosperous, and honorable life one earth, a blessed end, and life euerlasting. Moreover, O Lord, graunt unto her Majesties most honorable Councellors and eueri other member of this thy Churche of England, that they and wee our seuerell colleages may tryly and godlye serve thee." (fol. 98r) "That it may please thee to keepe and strengthen in the true worshipping of thee, in righteousnes and holiness of lyfe, your seruant Elizabeth our most gracious Queene and gouernour."
    The manuscript contains the following ownership inscriptions. Robert Cooke: name stamped on upper cover); fol 13v and rear pastedown: Michael Blesett ("Michael Blessett his Booke"), 17th century(?). fol 13v: Thomas Slynn ("thomas slynn his book god give him grace therein to Looke"), 17th century; fol. 113v, Anthony Bate ("Anthony Bate," written in pale red ink)., 17th century(?). John Meade Falkner (1858-1932) purchased the manuscript at Sotheby's, 12 December 1932, lot 86. Purchased at the foregoing sale through the London antiquarian bookseller Bernard Quaritch. Later in the library of Robert S. Pirie (1934-2015). See The Collection of Robert S. Pirie, Volumes I & II: Books and Manuscripts, December 2-5, 2015 (New York: Sotheby's, 2015), lot 661.
- 32101038566772 (Box 45)
- 32101038566780 (Box 46)
- 32101038560890 (Box 47)
- 32101080517053 (Box 40)
- 32101080517061 (Box 41)
- 32101080517079 (Box 42)
- 32101080517087 (Box 43)
- 32101080517095 (Box 44)
- 32101047409014 (Unitid 178)
- 32101047409022 (Unitid 179)
- 32101047409030 (Unitid 180)
- 32101047409048 (Unitid 181)
- 32101047409071 (Unitid 184)
- 32101047409055 (Unitid 182)
- 32101047409063 (Unitid 183)
- 32101047409097 (Unitid 186)
- 32101047409089 (Unitid 185)
- 32101047409105 (Unitid 187)
- 32101047409113 (Unitid 188)
- 32101047409121 (Unitid 189)
- 32101047409139 (Unitid 190)
- 32101047409147 (Unitid 191)
- 32101047409154 (Unitid 192)
- 32101047409196 (Unitid 196)
- 32101047409170 (Unitid 194)
- 32101047409162 (Unitid 193)
- 32101047409188 (Unitid 195)
- 32101047409212 (Unitid 198)
- 32101047409204 (Unitid 197)
- 32101047409220 (Unitid 199)
- 32101047409238 (Unitid 200)
- 32101047409246 (Unitid 201)
- 32101047409253 (Unitid 202)
- 32101047409261 (Unitid 203)
- 32101047409279 (Unitid 204)
- 32101047409295 (Unitid 206)
- 32101047407539 (Unitid 32)
- 32101047409287 (Unitid 205)
- 32101047409303 (Unitid 207)
- 32101047407521 (Unitid 31)
- 32101080516303 (Unitid 222)
- 32101047407547 (Unitid 33)
- 32101047407554 (Unitid 34)
- 32101037557855 (Unitid 220)
- 32101047407562 (Unitid 35)
- 32101047407588 (Unitid 37)
- 32101047407570 (Unitid 36)
- 32101047418502 (Unitid 38)
- 32101047408990 (Unitid 176)
- 32101047407596 (Unitid 39)
- 32101037674072 (Unitid 214)
- 32101047407604 (Unitid 40)
- 32101047407612 (Unitid 41)
- 32101047407620 (Unitid 42)
- 32101047409543 (Unitid 43)
- 32101047407638 (Unitid 44)
- 32101047407646 (Unitid 45)
- 32101047407653 (Unitid 46)
- 32101047407661 (Unitid 47)
- 32101047407679 (Unitid 48)
- 32101047407687 (Unitid 49)
- 32101037557806 (Unitid 219)
- 32101047418544 (Unitid 208)
- 32101047407695 (Unitid 50)
- 32101047408263 (Unitid 108)
- 32101047407703 (Unitid 51)
- 32101047407711 (Unitid 52)
- 32101047407729 (Unitid 53)
- 32101047407745 (Unitid 55)
- 32101047407737 (Unitid 54)
- 32101047407752 (Unitid 56)
- 32101047407760 (Unitid 57)
- 32101047407778 (Unitid 58)
- 32101047407786 (Unitid 59)
- 32101047407794 (Unitid 60)
- 32101047407802 (Unitid 61)
- 32101037478011 (Unitid 215)
- 32101047407810 (Unitid 62)
- 32101047407828 (Unitid 63)
- 32101047407836 (Unitid 64)
- 32101047407844 (Unitid 65)
- 32101047407851 (Unitid 66)
- 32101047409717 (Unitid 67)
- 32101047407869 (Unitid 68)
- 32101047409550 (Unitid 69)
- 32101047407877 (Unitid 70)
- 32101047407885 (Unitid 71)
- 32101047407893 (Unitid 72)
- 32101047407901 (Unitid 73)
- 32101047407919 (Unitid 74)
- 32101047407927 (Unitid 75)
- 32101047408024 (Unitid 76)
- 32101047408032 (Unitid 77)
- 32101037672936 (Unitid 211)
- 32101047408057 (Unitid 79)
- 32101047408040 (Unitid 78)
- 32101047408065 (Unitid 80)
- 32101047408073 (Unitid 81)
- 32101047408081 (Unitid 82)
- 32101047408107 (Unitid 84)
- 32101047408099 (Unitid 83)
- 32101036961967 (Unitid 216)
- 32101047407935 (Unitid 85)
- 32101047407943 (Unitid 86)
- 32101047407950 (Unitid 87)
- 32101047407968 (Unitid 88)
- 32101080515875 (Unitid 224)
- 32101047407992 (Unitid 90)
- 32101047408008 (Unitid 91)
- 32101047408115 (Unitid 93)
- 32101047408016 (Unitid 92)
- 32101047408123 (Unitid 94)
- 32101047408131 (Unitid 95)
- 32101047408149 (Unitid 96)
- 32101047408156 (Unitid 97)
- 32101047408164 (Unitid 98)
- 32101047408172 (Unitid 99)
- 32101047408180 (Unitid 100)
- 32101047408198 (Unitid 101)
- 32101047408206 (Unitid 102)
- 32101047408214 (Unitid 103)
- 32101047408222 (Unitid 104)
- 32101037673769 (Unitid 213)
- 32101047408230 (Unitid 105)
- 32101047408248 (Unitid 106)
- 32101047408255 (Unitid 107)
- 32101047408271 (Unitid 109)
- 32101047408297 (Unitid 111)
- 32101047408313 (Unitid 113)
- 32101047408321 (Unitid 114)
- 32101047408289 (Unitid 110)
- 32101047408305 (Unitid 112)
- 32101047408347 (Unitid 116)
- 32101047408339 (Unitid 115)
- 32101047408354 (Unitid 117)
- 32101047408362 (Unitid 118)
- 32101047408370 (Unitid 119)
- 32101047408602 (Unitid 120)
- 32101036950853 (Unitid 217)
- 32101047408610 (Unitid 121)
- 32101047408388 (Unitid 122)
- 32101047408495 (Unitid 132)
- 32101047408479 (Unitid 130)
- 32101047408453 (Unitid 128)
- 32101037673793 (Unitid 212)
- 32101047408438 (Unitid 126)
- 32101047408446 (Unitid 127)
- 32101047408412 (Unitid 124)
- 32101047408461 (Unitid 129)
- 32101047408420 (Unitid 125)
- 32101047408487 (Unitid 131)
- 32101047408503 (Unitid 133)
- 32101047408511 (Unitid 134)
- 32101047408529 (Unitid 135)
- 32101047408537 (Unitid 136)
- 32101047408545 (Unitid 137)
- 32101047408628 (Unitid 143)
- 32101047408636 (Unitid 144)
- 32101047408693 (Unitid 149)
- 32101047408552 (Unitid 138)
- 32101047408685 (Unitid 148)
- 32101047408669 (Unitid 146)
- 32101047408560 (Unitid 139)
- 32101047408578 (Unitid 140)
- 32101047408677 (Unitid 147)
- 32101038560023 (Unitid 223)
- 32101047408586 (Unitid 141)
- 32101047408594 (Unitid 142)
- 32101047408701 (Unitid 150)
- 32101047408727 (Unitid 152)
- 32101047408719 (Unitid 151)
- 32101047408735 (Unitid 153)
- 32101037438221 (Unitid 210)
- 32101047408925 (Unitid 154)
- 32101047408917 (Unitid 155)
- 32101047408891 (Unitid 157)
- 32101047409006 (Unitid 177)
- 32101047408909 (Unitid 156)
- 32101047408883 (Unitid 158)
- 32101047408875 (Unitid 159)
- 32101047408867 (Unitid 160)
- 32101047408859 (Unitid 161)
- 32101047408842 (Unitid 162)
- 32101047408818 (Unitid 164)
- 32101047408784 (Unitid 166)
- 32101047408776 (Unitid 167)
- 32101051921631 (Unitid 209)
- 32101047408933 (Unitid 171)
- 32101047408941 (Unitid 172)
- 32101047408750 (Unitid 169)
- 32101047408743 (Unitid 170)
- 32101047408768 (Unitid 168)
- 32101047408974 (Unitid 174)
- 32101047408982 (Unitid 175)
- 32101080516204 (Box 1)
- 32101080516212 (Box 2)
- 32101036945531 (Box 1)
- 32101036945549 (Box 2)
- 32101047409360 (Volume 1)
- 32101047407984 (Volume 2)
- 32101047407976 (Volume 3)
- 32101047408396 (Volume 1)
- 32101047408404 (Volume 2)
- 32101047408644 (Volume 1)
- 32101047408651 (Volume 2)
- 32101047408826 (Volume 1)
- 32101047408834 (Volume 2)
- 32101047408792 (Volume 1)
- 32101047408800 (Volume 2)
- 32101047408958 (Volume 1)
- 32101047408966 (Volume 2)
- 32101080848391 (Unitid 227)
- 32101080848516 (Unitid 228)
- 32101080848649 (Unitid 229)
- 32101080848656 (Unitid 230)
- 32101078580618 (Unitid 231)
- 32101078580709 (Unitid 232)
- 32101086132782 (Unitid 233)
- 32101086132899 (Unitid 234)
- 32101078581400 (Unitid 235)
- 32101086134234 (Box 48)
- 32101086134903 (Unitid 236)